A Guide to the General Correspondence of the Virginia Navy Board, 1776-1787
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
A Guide to the General Correspondence of the Virginia Navy Board, 1776-1787
The Library of Virginia
51711
1.8 cubic feet
Navy Board
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Acquisition Information
No acquisition information available.
Biographical Information
Prior to the establishing the Navy Board, the Committee of Safety handled all naval matters in their jurisdiction. Because the administrative duties of the Committee of Safety continued to broaden throughout the Revolutionary War, a new government body was established to handle naval matters. The fifth revolutionary convention passed an ordinance at its May 1776 session establishing the Board of Commissioners to Superintend and Direct the Naval Affairs of this Colony, also known as the Navy Board. The board had responsibility for all matters concerning the State Navy, which included building and maintaining warships, purchasing small vessels to sustain trade within the Chesapeake Bay, providing food and clothing to their personnel, opposing the enemy in the bay, organizing the transportation of troops, purchasing or obtaining munitions and arms to send to warships, recruiting seamen, and contracting workmen for the repair of ships at port. These duties fell to the five newly appointed commissioners of the Navy Board: Thomas Whiting, John Hutchings, Campion Travis, Thomas Newton, Jr., and George Webb. Only Thomas Whiting would serve in this position throughout the war. When the Navy Board was created the four different river defense forces (the James, York, Rappahannock and Potomac) were combined into one united Virginia State Navy.
Scope and Content
These records contain general correspondence regarding the supply of ships and shipyards, problems with privateers, filling naval crews, hiring temporary free and slave labor, provisions, tobacco shipments outside the United States, personal correspondence regarding wages, commissioning the construction of flat-bottom boats, prisoner exchanges, and the sale of state vessels. These records also include ship's payroll records, disbursement receipts relating to the cost of provisions, contracts, council orders, journal entries, and accounts, including those related to tobacco shipments outside of the United States. Records are separated by general correspondence related to specific vessels and other general correspondence.
Correspondents include Carter Braxton, Rawleigh Colston, Francis Fauquier, William Frazer, Patrick Henry, Thomas Jefferson, John Webb (Paymaster)' the Marquis de Lafayette and vessel captains.
Vessel captains include: John Archer [Liberty (Sloop) and Molly (Schooner)]; William Aylett [Speedwell (Schooner)]; Commodore James Barron [Liberty (Boat)]; Richard Barron [Patriot (Schooner)]; George Chamberlain [Fly (Boat)]; Thomas Chamberlayne [Tartar (Ship)]; Benjamin Day [Northampton (Brig)]; Pharoah Fitzpatrick [Peace and Plenty (Schooner)]; Thomas Grant [Jefferson (Brig)]; James Grey [Liberty (Brig)]; John Harris [Accomac (Galley) and Oliver Cromwell (Ship)]; Thomas Herbert [Liberty (Brig)]; James Hobb [Hornet (Schooner)]; Francis Kirby [Eastern Shore Betsey (Schooner)]; Paul Loyal [Harrison (Schooner) and Patriot (Boat)]; Nathaniel Mason [Industry (Ship)]; James Maxwell [Cormorant (Ship)]; Henry Mitchell [Favourite (Ship)]; Thomas Mitchell [Jefferson (Brig)]; Andrew Monroe [Jefferson (Brig)]; William Morris [Northampton (Brig)]; George Nicholson [Jefferson (Brig)]; Thomas Place [Relief (Schooner)]; Joseph Sanders [Dragon (Ship)]; William Skinner [Congress (Sloop)]; Thomas Smith [Hornet (Schooner)]; Robert Sully [Congress (Sloop)]; John Teackel [Diligence (Galley)]; Richard Timberland [Jefferson (Brig)]; John Webb [Lewis (Galley); William Webb [Jane (Ship)]; Wright Wescott [Henry (Galley)]; Joseph Wrenn [Defiance (Schooner), Dolly Henry (Sloop) and Liberty (Sloop); and John Young [Betsey (Schooner), Liberty (Sloop) and Mayflower (Schooner)].
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically.
Contents List
- Series I. General Correspondence of the Virginia Navy Board, 1776-1787.
  - General correspondence - Vessels.
    - Accomac (Galley), 1779-1780. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Betsey (Schooner), 1778-1779. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Congress (Sloop), 1777-1778. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Cormorant (Ship), 1781-1783. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Defiance (Schooner), 1778. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Diligence (Galley), 1780, 1782. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Dolphin (Ship), 1776 March. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Dragon (Ship), 1776, 1778-1779. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Dolly Henry (Sloop), 1778. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Eastern Shore Betsey (Schooner), 1778. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Experiment (Schooner), 1778. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Favourite (Ship), 1780. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Fly (Boat), 1779. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Greyhound (Brig), 1778. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Gloucester (Ship), 1780. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Hampton (Brig), 1778. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Harrison (Schooner), 1783. (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Henry (Galley), 1776, 1778. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Hero (Galley), 1776-1777, 1779. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Hornet (Schooner), 1777-1779. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Industry (Ship), 1776. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Jane (Ship), 17. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Jefferson (Brig), 1779-1781. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Le Committee (Schooner), 1781-1782. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Lee (Galley), 17. (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Lee (Pilot Boat), 1777. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Lewis (Galley), 1776-1777, 1781. (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Liberty (Boat), 1779, 1782-1783. (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Liberty (Sloop), 1777-1778. (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Liberty (Brig), 1777-1778. (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Lively (Sloop), 1777. (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Loyalist (Ship), 1782. (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Manley (Galley), 1776-1777, 1779. (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Matapony (Galley), 1776. (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Mayflower (Schooner), 1777-1778. (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Molly (Schooner), 1777-1778. (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Nicholson (Boat), 1780. (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Northampton (Brig), 1777-1779. (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Oliver Cromwell (Ship), 1771-1782. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Page (Galley), undated. (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Patriot and Liberty - payrolls (Schooners), 1785-1787. (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Patriot (Schooner), 1784-1787. (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Patriot (Boat), 1779, 1783-1784. (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Patriot (Schooner), 1787. (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Peace and Plenty (Schooner), 1778-1779. (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Raleigh (Brig), 1777. (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Relief (Schooner), 1778. (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Richmond (Barge), 1783. (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Rochester (Brig), 1777-1778. (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Safeguard (Galley), 1777. (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Scorpion (Sloop), undated. (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Shore (Sloop), 1777. (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Speedwell (Schooner), 1777-1778. (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Tartar (Ship), 1776-1778. (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Tempest (Ship), 1779-1781. (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Virginia (Packet), 1775. (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - York (Barge), undated. (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - General correspondence - Other.
    - Boat Yards: Mouth of Georges Creek, Decker's Creek and Pidgeon Cree - receipts for supplies and services, 1781. (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Commissioners for the Defense of the Chesapeake Bay, 1782, 1785, 1787. (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Contracts for building vessels, 1776. (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Council Orders, 1780-1781. (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Flat Bottom Boats (Lafayette), 1781. (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Index to Sections A and C of Papers Concerning the State Navy, Vol. 1, 1776-1777, 1780. (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Index (Old), Vol. 1 and Vol. 2, 1776-1777. (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Journal of State Agent relating primarily to the Navy, 1777 December 19-1778 April 15. (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Letters - Navy Board to Frazer and Roan, 1776-1777, 1779-1781. (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - List of officers and seamen, 1776-1779, 1784. (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - McClurg, Walter, Dr. (Surgeon), 1778-1779. (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Miscellaneous accounts - majority with William Frazer and pertaining to no particular vessel, 1776-1783. (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Navy Board accounts with Cornelius DeForrest, 1778. (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Navy Board accounts with Isaac Zane (Marlboro Iron Works), 1777-1778. (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Prisoner exchange from Bermuda, 1782-1783. (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Report of sale of galleys Accomac and Diligence, 1781-1782. (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Row galleys, 1776-1777. (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Webb, John (Paymaster) - Accounts primarily with individuals, 1780-1781. (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Webb, John (Paymaster) - Accounts primarly of department), 1776-1783. (Box 4, Folder 18)